# JINHAO LIANG

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am particularly interested in enabling a more reliable and efficient power grid from a computer science perspective, mainly through learning and optimization methodologies. Currently, my research topics include: 1) Developing robust and efficient algorithms to manage uncertainties in power system operations and electric vehicle charging; 2) Designing effective energy forecasting algorithms for both system-level and residential-level applications.

## **EDUCATION**

The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen Sep. 2022 - Jul. 2024 (expected)

M.Phil in Computer and Information Engineering GPA: 3.87/4.00

Advisor: Prof. Chenye Wu

Xidian University Sep. 2018 - Jun. 2022

B.E. in Software Engineering GPA: 3.70/4.00

## **PUBLICATIONS**

## Journal Articles

- 1. **Jinhao Liang**, Wenqian Jiang, Chenbei Lu and Chenye Wu, "Joint Chance-constrained Unit Commitment: Statistically Feasible Robust Optimization with Learning-to-Optimize Acceleration." revision submitted to *IEEE Transactions on Power Systems*, 2023
- Chenbei Lu, Jinhao Liang, Nan Gu, Haoxiang Wang and Chenye Wu, "Manipulation-Proof Virtual Bidding Mechanism Design." accepted by *IEEE Transactions on Energy Markets*, *Policy and Regulation*, 2023.
- 3. Chenbei Lu, **Jinhao Liang**, Wenqian Jiang, Jiaye Teng and Chenye Wu, "High-Resolution Probabilistic Load Forecasting: A Learning Ensemble Approach." accepted by **Journal of the Franklin Institute**, 2023

## Conference Proceedings

- 1. Jinhao Liang, Chenbei Lu, Wenqian Jiang and Chenye Wu, "Few-shot Residential Load Fore-casting Boosted by Learning to Ensemble." accepted by the 7th IEEE Conference on Energy Internet and Energy System Integration (EI<sup>2</sup>), 2023
- 2. Wenqian Jiang, **Jinhao Liang**, Chenbei Lu and Chenye Wu, "Robust Online EV Charging Scheduling with Statistical Feasibility." accepted by **the 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)**, 2023
- 3. **Jinhao Liang**, Wenqian Jiang and Chenye Wu, "Effective Carbon Tax Learning via Cap and Trade." accepted by *IEEE 5th International Electrical and Energy Conference (CIEEC)*, 2022

## SELECTED RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Joint Chance-constrained Unit Commitment with Statistical Feasibility

Supervior: Prof. Chenye Wu Oct. 2022 - Jun. 2023

- Extended the notion of statistical feasibility into unit commitment, a mixed-integer problem, and formulated the statistically feasible unit commitment.
- Developed sample-based uncertainty set construction algorithms, yielding less conservative solutions
- Accelerated the solving process from a learning-to-optimize perspective and designed the optimization kernel to boost its computational efficiency further.

# A Learning Ensemble Approach for Probabilistic Load Forecasting

Supervior: Prof. Chenye Wu

Jun. 2022 - Jul. 2023

- Proposed the learning ensemble framework, which can capture the optimal nonlinear combination of different single models.
- Developed the clustering-based few-shot learning methods to augment the data if data is limited.
- Demonstrated the performance guarantee of learning ensemble framework and clustering-based few-shot learning methods.

### SELECTED HONORS

Modern Chinese Scientists Scholarship (top 12 in Xidian University)

Jan. 2022

National Scholarship (2% in Xidian University)

Dec. 2021

### **SKILLS**

## **Programming Languages and Frameworks**

Python, Pytorch, MATLAB

### Languages

Chinese: native; English: professional working proficiency